Roger Griswold Papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Roger Griswold Papers
1781-1813
Connecticut Historical Society
Griswold, Roger
Collection consists of correspondence, transcriptions of speeches and proclamations as congressman and as Governor of Connecticut.
0.50 linear foot (1 box)
Related Material
An index of catalog cards is available to access Griswold related material in other collections at the item level. Access is through writer, recipient and date. The card catalog is located in the Research Center reading room.
Transcriptions of Griswold correspondence collected by Wolcott G. Lane in the 1940s and 1950s can be found in the Wolcott G. Lane Papers at the Connecticut Historical Society.
Biographical Sketch
Roger Griswold, Son of Matthew and Ursula (Wolcott ) Griswold was born in Lyme, Connecticut on May 21, 1762. He was graduated at Yale College in 1780 and until admitted to the bar in 1783 worked in his father's office, studying law. He immediately settled to practice in Norwich, returning to Lyme in 1798.
In October, 1798 Griswold married Fanny Rogers daughter of Colonel Zabdiel and Elizabeth (Tracy) Rogers.
In 1794 he entered the Connecticut Legislature, only to be elected to the House of Representatives in September of the same year. He did not return to political life in Connecticut until 1807, serving on the benches of the Supreme and Superior Courts of the State. In 1809, upon the death of Governor Jonathan Trumbull, Griswold was elected to Lieutenant Governor. In 1811 he was returned as Governor and remained in this office until his death.
With popular and official state approval, Griswold was strongly opposed to the war with Great Britain, and went so far as to refuse to place Connecticut militia under the command of the national government. The resulting constitutional arguments continued after Griswold's death on October 25, 1812.
Scope and Content
Collection consists predominantly of correspondence, the majority of which are transcriptions of letters written by Roger Griswold during the period 1781 - 1812. Of original material in this collection, correspondence is largely personal and addressed to Fanny Griswold, Elizabeth Griswold and Juliette Griswold. Also included are some papers and correspondence of Charles L. Boalt.
Arrangement
Materials are organized into six series, based on previous arrangement.
Series I: Letters to Fanny Griswold consists of personal letters written to his wife, Fanny Griswold, between February 19th, 1796 and December 27, 1801 whilst in Philadelphia and Washington. The letters are of a personal nature, discussing family business and the health of family members, but frequently contain news of political affairs.
Series II: Letters to Elizabeth Griswold (Boalt) consists of personal letters written to Elizabeth Griswold from family and friends.
Series III: Letters to Juliette Griswold consists of two personal letters written to Juliette Griswold from friends.
Series IV: Charles L. Boalt Correspondence consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings and printed circulars concerning the Hyde family.
Series V: Report on Provisions Inspected for Export consists of a report of beef and pork inspected and branded in the counties of Connecticut for the year 1811. The report was submitted to Governor Roger Griswold by Elizuh Goodrich.
Series VI: Cedric L. Robinson Transcriptions consists of transcriptions of letters written by Roger Griswold during the period September, 1781 - October, 1812. Transcriptions are arranged chronologically into four fascicles. The letters are of mixed personal and business content, many of which comment on political affairs conducted in the House of Representatives and the Senate.
Materials in this collection are arranged chronologically in each series to compliment access points from the card catalog.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is open, additional material is not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Griswold, Fanny Rogers.; Boalt, Elizabeth Griswold.; Griswold, Juliette.; Goodrich, Elizur.; Boalt, Charles.
Subjects
Meat inspection Connecticut.
Geographic Names
Connecticut Politics and government 1775-1865.; United States Politics and government 1801-1815.
Genre Forms
Holographs; holographs, signed; typescripts.
Contents:
- I. Letters to Fanny Griswold
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., February 19, 1796.; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., February 23, 1796.; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., April 13, 1796; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., May 9, 1796; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., May 14, 1796; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold,., May 19, 1796; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., May 26, 1796; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., December 12, 1796; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., December 16, 1796; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., March 1, 1797; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., March 1, 1797; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., December 8, 1797; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., January, 1798; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., December 23, 1799; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter to Fanny Griswold., December 27, 1801; (1 item); Folder contains transcription of letter. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- II. Letters to Elizabeth Griswold (Boalt)
  - Letters to Elizabeth Griswold (Boalt)., 1818 - 1846; (8 items) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- III. Letters to Juliette Griswold
  - Letters to Juliette Griswold., [18--?]; (2 items) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- IV. Charles L. Boalt Correspondence
  - Charles L. Boalt Correspondence., [1823 - 1862]; (9 items) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- V. Report on Provisions Inspected for Export
  - Report on Provisions Inspected for Export., 1811; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder 19)
- VI. Cedric L. Robinson Transcriptions
  - Transcribed copies of Letters from Roger Griswold.(Fascicle 1-A)., September 1, 1811 - January 13, 1798; (1 fascicle) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Transcribed copies of Letters from Roger Griswold. (Fascicle 2-A)., January 18, 1798 - December 20, 1801; (1 fascicle) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Transcribed copies of Letters from Roger Griswold. (Fascicle 3-A)., January 1, 1801 - May 16, 1812; (1 fascicle) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Transcribed copies of Letters from Roger Griswold. (Fascicle 4-A)., May 12, 1812 - October 29, 1812; (1 fascicle) (Box 1, Folder 23)